## Sam Merham

11624 Alegre Dr. Dublin, CA 94568 Cellular ~ 925-548-4076sammerham@icloud.com

#### **PROFILE**

Customer-centric, performance-driven senior executive powered with more than 16 years of management experience in full-service hospitality operations. Possess stellar reputation in directing all facets of the industry utilizing broad background in providing hands-on leadership to achieve solid business results. Show paramount efforts in innovating hotel concepts as well as in addressing guests' needs and concerns to continuously improve service standards, quality, and profitability.

#### Qualifications:

•

- Multi-Brand PMS Experience
- Pre-Opening Experience
- EMS, HMS, PMS, ONQ
- Presentation and Training
- Staff Development and Motivation
- Budgeting and Expense Control
- In-depth technical proficiency in Microsoft applications.
- Strong ability to solve problems identify and find solutions.
- Excellent communication skills both verbal and written.
- Excellent organization and time management skills.
- · Remarkable interpersonal skills.
- Excellent listening skills.
- Deep and advanced accounting and mathematical skills.
- Exceptional ability to work well in a team.
- Uncommon ability to adaptable easily and learn guickly.
- Enviable ability to multi-task, remain calm and professional under stress.
- Exceptional ability to maintain a positive attitude, handle conflict and confrontation.
- Proven ability to establish structure and discipline in a department.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Sodexo

**Polaris Lounge, United Airlines, SFO** 

**August 2019 - March2020** 

## General Manager San Francisco

- Provide management and strong leadership oversight in the daily operations for SFO Polaris Lounge; (Named the Named Best Business Class Lounge in the World)
- Oversee services of Bar, Dining Room, Buffet, Quite Suites, Showers and Dessert/Coffee bar to serve more than 1500 high-profile guests every day.
- Manages through 5 salaried managers, 1 executive chef, 2 sous chefs, 13 supervisors and 175 union hourly employees to create an exceptional travel experience with innovative beverage and food offerings.
- Maintain open communication with our client and continually make changes to exceed expectations.
- Provides local leadership and strategic direction while developing team for new and emerging business solutions that sustain growth in the day to day operations.
- Focus on everything within the unit from financials, audits, safety and fostering/building strong employee and client relationships.

Compass Group Oath/Yahoo

**November 2018 – August 2019** 

General Manger Sunnyvale, CA

- Direct all contract management service operations at the account.
- Oversee all daily operations of the entire unit to serve more than 3500 guests every day.
- Oversee service cafe, 2 coffee bars, 12 micro kitchens and catering operations.
- Manages through 4 salaried managers, 1 executive chef, 3 sous chefs, 3 supervisors and 100 hourly employees.
- Maintain open communication with our client and continually make changes to exceed expectations.
- Provides local leadership and strategic direction while developing team for new and emerging business solutions that sustain growth in the day to day operations.
- Participates in employee meetings, reviews and training programs.
- Establishes and maintains good rapport with staff, client and guest and other departments.
- Manages financial acumen for all areas including financial reporting with sales reports P&L reports, writing and adhering to annual budgets and cash handling.

#### Sodexo

### January 2015 - November 2018

## **San Ramon Valley Conference Center**

119 Guest rooms – 40 meeting rooms

## Operations Manager II San Ramon, CA

- Monitor and supervise the overall activities of Front Office, Reservations, Housekeeping, Janitorial and Banquet Set-up Operations.
- Attend and respond to guests' requests, enquiries, complaints and compliments.
- Ensure that proper training and procedures are in place to ensure provision of quality services
- Ensure that the guests receive warm attention and personal recognition
- Orchestrate and maintain distinctive and memorable service and operational standards, promoting unity and teamwork between all departments.
- Create a culture and an atmosphere of pride of property and guest satisfaction.
- Develop associate morale and ensure training of Guest Services associates.
- Participate in required M.O.D. program as scheduled.
- Conduct interview and hire staff, as required
- Sets objectives for each department and supervises the department supervisor.
- Any other duties assigned by the general manager.

#### Sodexo

## **Pacific Energy Conference Center**

March 2018 – May2018

## Interim General Manager San Francisco - CA

- Direct all contract management service operations.
- Plan and supervises special functions.
- Maintain cash control and payroll records.
- Hire and trains unit personnel.
- Maintain customer satisfaction and good public relations.
- Manage through managers and is accountable for the contract.
- Provide local leadership and strategic direction while developing team for new and emerging business solutions that sustain growth in the day to day operations.
- Provide team leadership & training.
- Control unit financials
- Directs daily food operations for quality & safety standards
- Supervise day to day activities.
- Delegate authority
- Assign & prioritize activities
- Monitor operating standards
- Establish a safe work environment
- Support workplace inclusion activities

**Holiday Inn** 

August 2013 – September 2014

- Orchestrate and maintain distinctive and memorable service and operational standards, promoting unity and teamwork between all departments.
- Create a culture and an atmosphere of pride of hotel and guest satisfaction.
- Demonstrate an eye for detail with excellent leadership style.
- Deliver and sustaining "Reputable" status for hotel OSAT scores
- Deliver a superior, unique and differentiated guest experience at the hotel; and empowering staffers
- Innovate a robust VIP, and guest recognition program that is consistent in all departments
- Supervise the overall activities of Front Office, Housekeeping and Maintenance operations.
- Sets objectives for each department within the rooms division and supervises the department manager.
- Implements the approved budget; monitors revenues and costs on a daily basis and takes corrective action when necessary.
- Possess strong cost management / operating margin skills.
- Control labor costs and expenses, and maximize effectiveness within all areas of responsibility.
- Coordinate capital improvement projects to maintain / upgrade quality standards and property image.
- Schedule and conduct routine Internal Inspections as de-facto Manager on Duty
- Conduct comprehensive monthly departmental meetings to include review of procedures and events which warrant special handling and detailed information
- Prepare and submit statistical, performance, and forecast analyses; including staff evaluations
- Disciplines staff or seek recourse to ensure that discipline and professionalism is upheld in the respective departments.

#### **Pleasanton Marriott Hotel**

**July 2008 – August 2013** 

242 guest rooms

<u>Director of Front Office Operations</u>

Pleasanton, CA

- Monitor daily performance with front office staff.
- Work closely with Cluster Director of Revenue Management to ensure all restrictions are set, as well as special events, and pricing.
- Create and produce reports as required.
- Coordinate schedules, payroll and expenses to meet or fall below budget.
- Participates in property initiatives.
- Ensure that group arrival, registration and check-out specifications and needs are executed.
- Ensure that guest data and management reporting is processed efficiently and accurately while maintaining proper security standards.
- Ensure that all accounting transaction and cash handling procedures are in compliance.
- Conduct regular monthly meetings with members of the Front Office and Communication Team to address current initiatives, projects and long term goals.
- Assist housekeeping in day-to-day activities.
- Pro-actively identify potential guest issues and represent property management in any resolutions and decisions related to front office.
- Recruit, hire, train and retain associates for all supervised departments.
- Develop monthly training items to foster development and cross training with other departments.
- Perform associate evaluations, provide coaching and development.
- Monitor guest satisfaction processes, and respond to guest concerns, and inquiries.

# Walnut Creek Marriott November 2007

May 2007 -

338guest rooms

Front Office Manager
Walnut Creek, CA

- Monitor and supervise the activities of front office staff, from maintaining proper cash control to guest service standards
- Attend and respond to guests' requests, enquiries, complaints and compliments
- Responsible for monitoring departmental costs to ensure performance against budget
- Ensure that proper training and procedures are in place to ensure provision of quality services
- Supervise front desk to ensure optimum occupancy and average room rate for purpose of maximizing revenue
- Ensure that the guests receives warm attention and personal recognition
- Update other operating departments, notably Housekeeping of all Front Office matters that concerns them
- Coordinate front office activities of the hotel and resolve problems arising from guests' complaints, reservation unusual requests and inquiries

- Prepare and update reports to the General Manager of the hotel
- Discuss and cooperate with other department heads to ensure coordination of hotel activities
- Conduct interview and hire front office staff, as required

## **Embassy Suites Hotel**

Cambridge University

**January 2006 – May 2007** 

### Front Office Supervisor Walnut Creek, CA

- Oversee and supervise all duties performed by all Front Office employees.
- Coach, counsel and discipline employees when necessary, using proper documentation and proper techniques.
- Ensure that all Front Office employees complete their essential duties before their departure.
- Ensure that all Front Office employees are posted at their stations at posted time.
- Assist with all sick calls or tardiness by finding proper coverage, report to work and stay until proper coverage can be found.
- Assist with any scheduled shift problems on the night audit shifts.
- Accountable for the proper training and daily monitoring of all service levels provided by employees to guests and other fellow employees.
- Monitor and maintain proper Front Office operational supplies.
- Accountable for meeting and coming in under payroll and expense budgets.
- Accountable for maintaining and monitoring that all employees follow proper cash handling procedures.
- Ensure proper inventory controls, working with Sales and Reservations to ensure maximum selling potential and house balance.

### **EDUCATIONAL & PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT**

Cambridge University					
•	Certificate of IELTS	2004			
NAATI, Australia					
•	Diploma of translation	2004			
Helwan University					
•	Bachelor's Degree of Arts		2001		
Embassy Suites Hotel					
•	Employee of the month	2006			
•	Employee of the month	2007			
Pyramid Hotel Group					
•	Manager of the 1 <sup>st</sup> Quarter	2010			
•	Manager of the year	2010			
•	Manager of the 2 <sup>nd</sup> Quarter	2011			
•	Nominee for Manager of the 3 <sup>rd</sup> Quarter	2011			
Marriott Corporation					
•	Front Office Leadership	2011			
•	Full Service Property Management Systems - System Administration	2011			
•	Revenue Analysis	2011			
•	MARSHA Basics		2010		
•	Revenue Management Skills	2010			
•	Effective Presentations	2010			
•	Service Excellence	2007/2	2009		

#### Sodexo

•	Spirit of Inclusion	2015
•	Equal Employment opportunity & affirmative Action training	2015
•	Clients for life: Attitude & Action	2015
OSHA		
•	OSHA Standards for General Industry - OSHA 511	2016
CPR Certification		2015
ServSa	afe Certification	2015/2018